<?xml version="1.0"?>
 <fullText>   <siteTitle>OWDI Drought</siteTitle>   <readMore>Read More &gt;&gt;</readMore>   <hideText>Hide Text</hideText>   <welcomeText>Welcome to Colorado River Basin Drought</welcomeText>   <coDroughtHeader>Colorado River Basin Drought</coDroughtHeader>   <welcomeTitle>Drought in the Colorado River Basin</welcomeTitle>   <welcomeSub>Insights using open data</welcomeSub>   <scroll>Scroll down to view this application.</scroll>   <appExplanation1>Since 2000, the Colorado River Basin (Basin) has been experiencing an historic, extended drought that has impacted regional water supply and other resources, such as hydropower, recreation, and ecologic services. During this time, the Basin has experienced its lowest 16-year period of inflow in over 100 years of record keeping and reservoir storage in the Colorado River system has declined from nearly full to about half of capacity. Since 2000, the Colorado River Basin (Basin) has been experiencing an historic, extended drought that has impacted regional water supply and other resources, such as hydropower, recreation, and ecologic services. During this time, the Basin has experienced its lowest 16-year period of inflow in over 100 years of record keeping and reservoir storage in the Colorado River system has declined from nearly full to about half of capacity.</appExplanation1>   <appExplanation2>Entities that rely on Colorado River water are concerned with the impacts of the ongoing drought and declining reservoir levels, such as decreasing water supply and the possibility of a first ever shortage condition in the Lower Basin, decreasing hydropower capacities at Lake Powell and Lake Mead, the potential for loss of hydroelectric generation at Lake Powell, reduced recreational opportunities, and changes to in-stream flows that support ecologic services.</appExplanation2>   <appExplanation3>In response to drought conditions, Federal agencies and stakeholders throughout the Basin have been working together to find creative ways to reduce the impacts of the drought for the people and resources that rely on water from the Colorado River.</appExplanation3>   <appExplanation4>This Colorado River Basin Drought Visualization, developed by the Department of the Interior (Department), the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), and the Bureau of Reclamation (Reclamation), is a Pilot Project to support the Department's Open Water Data Initiative (OWDI). The Pilot Project is part of a multi-agency effort to showcase the usefulness of open data (i.e., data provided in a discoverable, sharable, and machine-readable format) by exploring the current 16-year drought and its impacts in the Colorado River Basin.</appExplanation4>   <appExplanation5>Scroll down to learn more about the importance of the Colorado River, the impacts of the current drought, and the ways in which the drought is being managed in the Basin.</appExplanation5>   <appExplanation6>For more information about the OWDI, please visit the Advisory Committee on Water Information &lt;a href="http://acwi.gov/spatial/owdi/" target="_blank"&gt;OWDI website&lt;/a&gt;.</appExplanation6>   <mainMessage1>The Colorado River is a lifeline.</mainMessage1>   <coRiverLifeline1>Water from the Colorado River is essential for life in portions of the southwestern United States and northwestern Mexico. According to the Bureau of Reclamation (2012), the Colorado River system: </coRiverLifeline1>   <coRiverLifeline2>Supplies more than 1 in 10 Americans with some, if not all of their water for municipal use, including drinking water.</coRiverLifeline2>   <coRiverLifeline3>Provides irrigation water to more than 5.5 million acres (approximately 8,590 square miles) of land.</coRiverLifeline3>   <coRiverLifeline4>Serves at least 22 Federally recognized tribes.</coRiverLifeline4>   <coRiverLifeline5>Supports 4,200 megawatts of electrical generating capacity, enough to power hundreds of local areas and millions of people in the seven Basin States.</coRiverLifeline5>   <coRiverLifeline6>Serves eleven National Parks, four National Recreation Areas, and seven National Wildlife Refuges, supporting over $1 billion in tourism revenue associated with outdoor recreation and wildlife.</coRiverLifeline6>   <coRiverLifeline7>Provides habitat for &lt;a href="http://www.fws.gov/endangered/esa-library/pdf/ESA_basics.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;threatened and endangered&lt;/a&gt; wildlife and vegetation species, as well as other native species.</coRiverLifeline7>   <coRiverLifeline8>Bureau of Reclamation, 2012. Colorado River Basin Water Supply and Demand Study.</coRiverLifeline8>   <suppInfo>Supporting Info</suppInfo>   <mainMessage5>One river, two parts.</mainMessage5>   <basinDivided1>Approximately 1,400 miles long, flowing through seven states and Mexico, the Colorado River drains roughly one-twelfth of the land area of the contiguous United States.  The Colorado River Basin is divided into Upper and Lower Basins at the Lee Ferry compact point located in northern Arizona. The Upper Basin spans portions of Wyoming, Colorado, New Mexico, Utah, and northern Arizona, and the Lower Basin spans portions of Nevada, Arizona, California, and western New Mexico. The Colorado River also supplies water to portions of northwestern Mexico, in the states of Baja California and Sonora, and serves at least 22 Federally-recognized Native American Tribes and Communities located within the Basin.</basinDivided1>   <basinDivided2>The Upper Colorado River Basin supplies most of the water for the Basin. Of the total water supply from the Upper Basin, about 50 percent of streamflow comes from baseflow (Rumsey et al., 2015). Most baseflow is water that originates as precipitation and snowmelt in the Rocky and Wasatch Mountains, replenishes local groundwater supplies, and resurfaces as streamflow that feeds Upper Basin reservoirs. The Lower Basin is arid with little tributary runoff reaching the mainstream of the Colorado River except during occasional rain events.  The Lower Basin is dependent upon managed use of the Colorado River system to make its land habitable and productive.  The importance of the Colorado River to the region it serves is underscored by the legal framework that governs its management.</basinDivided2>   <basinDivided3>Within the Basin is an interconnected system of rivers, dams, reservoirs, and water diversions that provides water for uses such as agriculture, municipal and domestic use, hydropower, ecosystems, and recreation. Colorado River water is also delivered to areas that lie outside the Basin's hydrologic boundary, including southwestern California, the east side of the Front Range in Colorado, and the west side of the Wasatch Range in Utah.</basinDivided3>   <basinDivided4>Resources and facilities within the Colorado River Basin are managed to accomplish their project goals in a manner fully consistent with applicable provisions of Federal law including the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/pao/lawofrvr.html" target="_blank"&gt;Law of the River&lt;/a&gt; and other project-specific operational guidelines. The Law of the River includes operating criteria, regulations, administrative decisions, Federal statutes, interstate compacts, court decisions and decrees, an international treaty, and contracts with the Secretary, and defines the responsibilities of the Secretary's water master role in the Lower Basin.</basinDivided4>   <basinDivided5>Rumsey, C.A., et al. 2015. "&lt;a href="http://water.usgs.gov/watercensus/file/Rumsey-et-al_2015.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Regional scale estimates of baseflow and factors influencing baseflow in the Upper Colorado River Basin&lt;/a&gt;." Journal of Hydrology: Regional Studies 4: 91-107.</basinDivided5>   <basinDivided6>For an overview of the Colorado River Basin and its network of reservoirs, water delivery infrastructure, and water delivery service areas, click button below.</basinDivided6>   <readMore>Read More &gt;&gt;</readMore>   <explore>Explore</explore>   <mainMessage2>The Colorado River is managed with a series of control structures that provide flood control, water conservation, and hydropower benefits.</mainMessage2>   <blueDragon1>The natural water supply of the Basin is highly variable from year-to-year. The ability to capture water during high flow years and to use this stored water in drier years has enabled Reclamation to meet resource needs throughout this drought period. Although the Basin is experiencing the worst 16-year drought in over 100 years of record, the system of reservoirs has provided multiple years of storage as designed and, throughout the drought, delivery commitments in both basins have been met.</blueDragon1>   <blueDragon2>In addition to providing storage for regional water supply and facilitating water deliveries, the dams and reservoirs in the Colorado River system also provide flood control benefits, improve navigation, and allow for the generation of hydroelectric power. The construction of these facilities have allowed for the development adjacent or nearby water delivery systems and management supports ancillary benefits such as other economic, cultural, and ecologic services.</blueDragon2>   <blueDragon3>In the Lower Basin, Hoover Dam was constructed pursuant to the 1928 Boulder Canyon Project Act (BCPA) for the purpose of controlling floods, improving navigation, regulating the river's flow, providing for water storage and delivery, and for the generation of electrical energy. The BCPA and subsequent construction of Hoover Dam in 1935 allowed for the construction of the Imperial Diversion Dam in 1938, the last diversion dam on the Colorado River for United States water users located north of Yuma, Arizona. From its head works, water is diverted into the All-American Canal on the California side of the dam and into the Gila Gravity Main Canal on the Arizona side of the dam. These diversions provide water to the Gila Project, the Yuma Project, the Imperial Irrigation District, the Coachella Valley Water District, and the City of Yuma, and through Siphon Drop and Pilot Knob to the Northerly International Boundary (NIB) for diversion at Morelos Dam in Mexico.</blueDragon3>   <blueDragon4>In 1938, Parker Dam was constructed to regulate water released from Hoover Dam and allowed for the construction of the W.P. Whitsett Intake Pumping Plant in 1940 and the Mark Wilmer Pumping Plant in 1993 (water diversions for the Metropolitan Water District of Southern California and Central Arizona Project, respectively). The construction of Davis Dam in 1953 provided additional regulation for water released from Hoover Dam. Water released from both of these facilities are made to satisfy beneficial use requirements of Lower Colorado River entitlement holders in the United States, deliver water to Mexico pursuant to the 1944 U.S.-Mexico Water Treaty, and to generate hydropower with these water releases.</blueDragon4>   <blueDragon5>The graphic below depicts the major dams, reservoirs, and control structures of the Lower Colorado River.</blueDragon5>   <blueDragon6>Click here for PDF version</blueDragon6>   <blueDragon7>USGS Texas Water Science Center App</blueDragon7>   <blueDragon8>To see realtime data and take a journey through major dams on the Lower Colorado River, click button below.</blueDragon8>   <mainMessageDirt>The western U.S. is experiencing an extended drought.</mainMessageDirt>   <dygraphsSection1>Since 2000, the Colorado River Basin has experienced the driest 16-year period in over 100 years of historical natural flows (Bureau of Reclamation, 2015) and one of the most severe droughts in the last 1,200 years (Meko et al., 2007a and 2007b).</dygraphsSection1>   <dygraphsSection2>Bureau of Reclamation, 2015. &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/NaturalFlow/index.html" target="_blank"&gt;Colorado River Basin Natural Flow and Salt Data website&lt;/a&gt;.</dygraphsSection2>   <dygraphsSection3>Meko, D.M., et al. 2007a. &lt;a href="ftp://ftp.ncdc.noaa.gov/pub/data/paleo/treering/reconstructions/northamerica/usa/upper-colorado-flow2007.txt" target="_blank"&gt;Upper Colorado River Flow Reconstruction&lt;/a&gt;. IGBP PAGES/World Data Center for Paleoclimatology. Data Contribution Series # 2007-052. NOAA/NCDC Paleoclimatology Program, Boulder CO, USA.</dygraphsSection3>   <dygraphsSection4>Meko, D.M., C.A. Woodhouse, C.H. Baisan, T. Knight, J.J. Lukas, M.K. Hughes, and M.W. Salzer. 2007b. &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2007GL029988/pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Medieval drought in the upper Colorado River Basin&lt;/a&gt;. Geophysical Research Letters, Vol. 34, L10705.</dygraphsSection4>   <dygraphsSection5>The &lt;a href="http://droughtmonitor.unl.edu/" target="_blank"&gt;U.S. Drought Monitor&lt;/a&gt; shows the extent and intensity of drought conditions in the Western U.S. over time from 2000 to 2015.</dygraphsSection5>   <dygraphsSection6>U.S. Drought Monitor</dygraphsSection6>   <waterSupplyVariableOverTime>Water supply is variable over time.</waterSupplyVariableOverTime>   <waterSupplyVariableContent1>Approximately 90 percent of the Basin's water supply comes from the Upper Basin. As a result, drought conditions in the Upper Basin impact water supply and resources in both the Lower Basin and the Upper Basin. Long-term drought like the Basin has experienced since 2000 reflects natural climate variability coupled with the likely impacts from changing climate and increased temperature over the past two decades.</waterSupplyVariableContent1>   <waterSupplyVariableContent2>The USGS stream gage at Lees Ferry, Arizona is the lowermost mainstream gage in the Upper Basin, located about 12 miles downstream of Glen Canyon Dam and about 1 mile upstream of the Compact Point between the Upper and Lower Basins. Natural flow at this gage location is used as a proxy for the hydrologic conditions in the Upper Basin and the overall hydrologic health of the Basin. Natural flow is defined as the streamflow that would have otherwise occurred without the effects of human activities such as reservoir regulation and depletion of water supply.</waterSupplyVariableContent2>   <waterSupplyVariableContent3>In the graphic above, the 10-year average &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/NaturalFlow/documentation.html"&gt;natural flow&lt;/a&gt; at Lees Ferry shows periods of below and above average annual flow (approximately 14.8 maf). The most recent drought for the 2000-2015 period (indicated by the brown shaded area) was the driest 16-year period in the past 100 years and one of the driest 16-year periods in the past 1,200 years. The graphic also depicts how during the early part of the 1900s, which corresponds to the period of reference used to set the apportionments for the Upper and Lower Basins in the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g1000/pdfiles/crcompct.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;1922 Colorado River Compact&lt;/a&gt;, was an unusually wet period (indicated by the green shaded area). At the time the 1922 Colorado River Compact went into effect, the average annual inflow at Lees Ferry was approximately 18.0 maf.</waterSupplyVariableContent3>   <waterSupplyVariableContent4>Historical observations are extended by a &lt;a href="{{baseUrl}}/treeringdata/index.html" target="_blank"&gt;tree-ring reconstruction&lt;/a&gt; of streamflow going back approximately 1,200 years, as estimated by Meko et al. (2007). Because trees grow less during dry years and more during wet years, tree-ring cores can be used to estimate historical streamflow conditions going back many centuries. Tree-ring core samples were collected from locations throughout the Upper Basin to estimate historical natural flow. These estimates were validated using the observed natural flow record developed by Reclamation.</waterSupplyVariableContent4>   <waterSupplyVariableContent5>Tree ring data thumbnail</waterSupplyVariableContent5>   <waterSupplyVariableContent6>To explore more about reconstructed natural flow based on tree ring data, click here.</waterSupplyVariableContent6>   <waterSupplyVariableContent7>Historical images of Lees Ferry Gage, reproduced from &lt;a href="http://pubs.usgs.gov/pp/pp1677/pdf/pp1677.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Topping et al. (2003)&lt;/a&gt;. (A) View downstream from Number 1 Gage, taken from the right bank of the Colorado River. At the time of this photograph on September 21, 1923, the river stage was 11.05 feet and discharge was 27,000 cubic feet per second. Photo credit: G.C. Stevens of the U.S. Geological Survey. Photo source: 1921-37 Surface Water Records File, Colorado River at Lees Ferry, Arizona, file stored at the Federal Records Center in Laguna Niguel, California, in Accession No. 57-78-0006, Box 2 of 2 , Location No. MB053635. (B) View from the edge of the dugway road downstream, September 22, 1923. Photo credit: G.C. Stevens of the U.S. Geological Survey.</waterSupplyVariableContent7>   <waterSupplyVariableContent8>USGS observations of the Colorado River at Lees Ferry have occured since 1895 through the present. For more information and data, visit the U.S. Geological Survey &lt;a href="http://waterdata.usgs.gov/nwis/wys_rpt/?site_no=09380000&amp;agency_cd=USGS" target="_blank"&gt;National Water Information System&lt;/a&gt;. Real-time gage height, discharge, water temperature, and water quality parameters can be accessed from the U.S. Geological Survey &lt;a href="http://www.gcmrc.gov/discharge_qw_sediment/station/GCDAMP/09380000" target="_blank"&gt;Grand Canyon Monitoring and Research Center website&lt;/a&gt;.</waterSupplyVariableContent8>   <waterSupplyVariableContent9>1922 Colorado River Compact</waterSupplyVariableContent9>   <waterSupplyVariableContent10>Bureau of Reclamation. 1922. &lt;a href="http://wwa.colorado.edu/resources/colorado-river/docs/compact/meeting19andforeward.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Minutes of the 19th meeting of the Colorado River Commission&lt;/a&gt;.</waterSupplyVariableContent10>   <waterSupplyVariableContent11>Bureau of Reclamation. 2012. &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/NaturalFlow/" target="_blank"&gt;Natural Flow and Salt Data&lt;/a&gt;.</waterSupplyVariableContent11>   <waterSupplyVariableContent12>Meko, D.M., C.A. Woodhouse, C.H. Baisan, T. Knight, J.J. Lukas, M.K. Hughes, and M.W. Salzer, 2007. &lt;a href="http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1029/2007GL029988/pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Medieval drought in the upper Colorado River Basin&lt;University of Arizona Lab of Tree-Ring Research/a&gt;. Geophysical Research Letters, Vol. 34, L10705.</waterSupplyVariableContent12>   <waterSupplyVariableContent13>University of Arizona Lab of Tree-Ring Research</waterSupplyVariableContent13>   <mainMessage3>The Colorado River Basin's abundant storage capacity has made the southwest more resilient to persistent drought.</mainMessage3>   <coBasinReservoir1>Basin-wide system storage totals about 60 maf, approximately four times the average annual inflow in the Upper Basin (14.8 maf). The Basin's two largest reservoirs, Lake Powell and Lake Mead, combine for about 50 maf of storage, approximately 83 percent of the total system storage. This large storage capacity creates a buffer against year-to-year hydrologic variability and longer-term drought periods by allowing the storage of excess water during wet years and the use of water from storage during dry years.</coBasinReservoir1>   <coBasinReservoir2>It is this large amount of Basin-wide storage that has allowed Reclamation to continue to meet water delivery requirements during the current drought period. It should be noted, however, that headwater reaches in the Upper Basin sometimes experience localized shortages due to insufficient in-stream flows during dry years.</coBasinReservoir2>   <coBasinReservoir3>Idaho under a foot of water</coBasinReservoir3>   <coBasinReservoir4>The volume of water that can be stored in the Colorado River system reservoirs (60 maf) is enough to cover the state of Utah in about one foot of water. Vertical and horizontal dimensions shown above are not to scale.</coBasinReservoir4>   <coBasinReservoir5>Bureau of Reclamation. Colorado River Basin Supply and Demand Study, 2012.</coBasinReservoir5>   <mainMessage4>Development in the West continues, leading to increased water use in the Colorado River Basin.</mainMessage4>   <waterUsage1>Since the early 1900s, water demand in the Colorado River Basin has increased while water supply has, on average, decreased. For the 15-year period preceding the signing of the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g1000/pdfiles/crcompct.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;1922 Colorado River Compact&lt;/a&gt;, when 7.5 maf was apportioned to both the Upper and Lower Basins, the average annual natural flow in the Upper Basin was about 18.0 maf. When the 1944 U.S.-Mexico Water Treaty was executed, the long-term average annual natural flow in the Upper Basin was about 16.3 maf. The current long-term average annual natural flow in the Upper Basin is about 14.8 maf (Bureau of Reclamation, 2015).</waterUsage1>   <waterUsage2>While the average annual natural flow has decreased since the early 1900s, the balance between water supply and water demand in the Colorado River system has been operating on increasingly close margins. As a result of this decrease in natural flows and an increase in water depletions basin-wide, it now appears that the Colorado River system is over-allocated (Bureau of Reclamation, 2012).</waterUsage2>   <waterUsage3>Climate projections indicate more extreme conditions are possible, with longer, more severe wet and dry periods. Cooperation and collaboration is key to finding sustainable solutions and addressing current and future challenges.</waterUsage3>   <waterUsage4>Trends in water supply and water use in the Colorado River Basin are shown above. When water use exceeds the water supply in a given year, water stored is reduced. During the past 20 years, average water supply and average water use have been about equal. Under these conditions, reservoirs are replenished much more slowly. Water supply and water use data in the graphic above are estimated by Reclamation using water accounting information, USGS &lt;a href="http://waterdata.usgs.gov/nwis/wys_rpt/?site_no=09380000&amp;agency_cd=USGS" target="_blank"&gt;stream gage data&lt;/a&gt;, and other sources.</waterUsage4>   <waterUsage5>In this graphic, water use is equal to "consumptive use" (surface water diversions and groundwater pumping minus measured and unmeasured return flows) as estimated by Reclamation in its &lt;a href=" http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/wtracct.html" target="_blank"&gt;annual water accounting reports&lt;/a&gt;. Other methods of estimating water use that account for withdrawals of surface and groundwater, and incorporate water that is used and returned to the stream, are made by the USGS.</waterUsage5>   <waterUsage6>Bureau of Reclamation. 2012. &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/programs/crbstudy/finalreport/index.html" target="_blank"&gt;Colorado River Basin Water Supply and Demand Study&lt;/a&gt;.</waterUsage6>   <waterUsage7>Discover current reservoir conditions in the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/uc/wcao/water/basin/tc_cr.html" target="_blank"&gt;Upper Basin&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/hourly/hourly.html" target="_blank"&gt;Lower Basin&lt;/a&gt;.</waterUsage7>   <mainMessage6>Because of reduced supply during the current drought, the elevations of Lakes Mead and Powell have declined.</mainMessage6>   <beforeAfter1>As the reservoir levels of Lake Mead and Lake Powell decline, other resources, such as hydropower and recreation, are also impacted.</beforeAfter1>   <beforeAfter2>In the photo slider above, the change in Lake Mead's surface area can be seen from the pre-drought conditions in 1999 to the current drought conditions as of 2014. The red area that emerges in the photo slide above represents the loss in the reservoir's surface area as Lake Mead's elevation has declined. Water surface area extent maps are based on &lt;a href="http://landsat.usgs.gov/" target="_blank"&gt;U.S. Geological Survey Landsat&lt;/a&gt; surface reflectance-corrected images acquired in the month of June in 1999 and 2014. For both composites, two Landsat images acquired within 16 days of each other have been merged to generate cloud-free composites suitable for measurement and change comparison.</beforeAfter2>   <beforeAfter3>Since 2001, Lake Mead's elevation dropped from 1,196 to 1,075 feet by June 2015 (a decline of 121 feet). As the upper photo slider shows, the decline in the reservoir elevation during this time has exposed a white band of mineralized rock around the shoreline. The declining reservoir level has also exposed Hoover Dam's four intake towers, two on the right side and two on the left side of the photo slider. Water from the reservoir flows through these intake towers at specified release volumes to meet downstream water demands in Arizona, California, Nevada, and Mexico, while producing hydropower as water flows through Hoover Dam's 17 hydroelectric turbines.</beforeAfter3>   <beforeAfter4>The lower photos show the conditions of Lake Mead and the upstream face of Hoover Dam in 2001 at elevation 1,196 feet (left photo) and the conditions in June 2015 at elevation 1,075 feet (center photo). The lower photos also show the Nevada spillway in the bottom right corner of the photos. There are two spillways at Hoover Dam, one on the Nevada side and one on the Arizona side of the dam. At higher reservoir levels, spillways would be use to bypass flow around the Hoover Dam powerplant to prevent water from overtopping the dam. When water reaches the top of the spillway drum gates, it flows into the spillways, bypassing the dam via a series of tunnels and re-entering the river channel below the dam.</beforeAfter4>   <beforeAfter5>Every 1-foot drop in the elevation of Lake Mead reduces Hoover Dam's powerplant capacity by approximately 5.7 megawatts (Reclamation estimate, as reported in Illia, 2010).  Since Lake Mead was last full in 2000, Hoover Dam's powerplant capacity has fallen from 2,074 to 1,563 megawatts (as of August 2015). Reclamation has mitigated some of this impact by replacing traditional turbines with "wide-head" turbines, which are capable of generating more efficiently at lower reservoir levels, and making significant efficiency improvements to the powerplant (Kuckro, 2014).</beforeAfter5>   <beforeAfter6>At Lake Powell, risk to the Glen Canyon Dam powerplant is related to declining reservoir levels and the potential for loss of generating capacity below elevation 3,490 feet. Based on Reclamation analysis conducted in August 2015, the earliest this is projected to occur is 2019 (about a 5 percent chance of occurring). Since Lake Powell finished filling in 1980, its water surface elevation has fallen to as low as elevation 3,555 feet (33 percent of capacity) in April 2005, approximately 65 feet above minimum power pool.</beforeAfter6>   <beforeAfter7>The photo slider above shows Hemenway Harbor, located the southwestern portion of Lake Mead, with the location of Las Vegas Marina at elevation 1,152 feet in January 2003, and the new location of Las Vegas Marina at elevation 1,078 feet in May 2015. The photos also depict the increased exposure of Lake Mead's shoreline and the emergence of the Boulder Islands, located on the right side of the photo, as the reservoir elevation declined.</beforeAfter7>   <beforeAfter8>Lake Mead's declining reservoir elevation has impacted marinas and boat launching facilities at the Lake Mead National Recreation Area, requiring the relocation of marinas and the extension of boat ramps to keep recreational facilities open. To continue to provide boat access as reservoir levels have declined, the National Park Service, responsible for Lake Mead National Recreation Area, has been &lt;a href="http://www.azcentral.com/news/articles/2010/11/01/20101101lake-mead-water-level-down.html" target="_blank"&gt;extending boat ramps since 2002&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://bouldercityreview.com/sections/news/lake-meadhoover-dam/lake-mead%E2%80%99s-level-rises-slightly.html" target="_blank"&gt;planned to spend $5 million extending ramps in 2015&lt;/a&gt;. Additional recreational impacts not shown in these photos include: In 2007, the Overton Beach marina became inoperable and facilities from Overton Beach were moved to two other marinas, Callville Bay and Temple Bar, located in Boulder Canyon and Temple Basin areas of Lake Mead, respectively. In 2008, Lake Mead Marina was moved from the location it had occupied since the 1960s to its current location in Hemenway Harbor.</beforeAfter8>   <beforeAfter9>Illia, T. 2010. &lt;a href="http://southwest.construction.com/southwest_contractor_news/2010/0927_LakeMeadLevel.asp" target="_blank"&gt;Big Drop in Lake Mead Level Curbs Hoover Water, Power&lt;/a&gt;. ENR Southwest website.</beforeAfter9>   <beforeAfter10>Kuckro, R., 2014. &lt;a href="http://southwest.construction.com/southwest_contractor_news/2010/0927_LakeMeadLevel.asp" target="_blank"&gt;Receding Lake Mead poses challenges to Hoover Dam's power output&lt;/a&gt;. E&amp;amp;E Publishing EnergyWire website.</beforeAfter10>   <mainMessage7>The possibility of a shortage condition in the Lower Basin may result in reduced water deliveries.</mainMessage7>   <lakeMeadStatic1>Consistent with the 2007 Interim Guidelines, if Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be 1,075 feet or lower based on an August projection, a Lower Basin shortage condition would be determined. Monthly projections made by Reclamation through an operational model called the "24-Month Study" are used to set the operational conditions for Lake Mead and Lake Powell.</lakeMeadStatic1>   <lakeMeadStatic2>Scroll down to learn more about Lake Mead's operational conditions, how operational conditions are determined, and the potential impacts on water deliveries in the Lower Basin.</lakeMeadStatic2>   <lakeMeadStatic3>&lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/programs/climateresearch/Charter_ModelingWorkGroup.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Bureau of Reclamation Colorado River Modeling Work Group Methods&lt;/a&gt; take into account temperature, snowpack, precipitation, consumptive use, and other factors, from many data sources beyond operations and observations made by the  Bureau of Reclamation. Other datasets include:</lakeMeadStatic3>   <lakeMeadStatic4>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Colorado River Basin River Forecast Center</lakeMeadStatic4>   <lakeMeadStatic5>U.S. Geological Survey Stream Gage Information</lakeMeadStatic5>   <lakeMeadStatic6>Reclamation's 24-Month Study reports:</lakeMeadStatic6>   <lakeMeadStatic7>Upper Colorado Region Water Operations</lakeMeadStatic7>   <lakeMeadStatic8>Lower Colorado Region Water Operations</lakeMeadStatic8>   <lakeMeadStatic9>2007 Record of Decision on Colorado River Interim Guidelines for Lower Basin Shortages and the Coordinated Operations for Lake Powell and Lake Mead (2007 Interim Guidelines)</lakeMeadStatic9>   <lakeMeadStatic10>Lake Mead's historical elevations since 2000, projected elevations for the next two years, and annual operating conditions are shown in the figure above.</lakeMeadStatic10>   <lakeMeadStatic11>Since the drought began in 2000, Lake Mead's elevation has declined by nearly 140 feet, declining every year except for 2005 and 2011. Projections of Lake Mead elevations are made by Reclamation and summarized in the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/24mo/index.html" target="_blank"&gt;Colorado River Basin 24-Month Study reports&lt;/a&gt;. The 24-Month Study is Reclamation's monthly operations model, simulating 12 major reservoirs in the Colorado River Basin on a monthly time step for a period of 24 months. These include nine reservoirs in the Upper Basin (Fontenelle, Flaming Gorge, Taylor Park, Blue Mesa, Morrow Point, Crystal, Vallecito, Navajo, and Lake Powell) and three reservoirs in the Lower Basin (Lake Mead, Lake Mohave, and Lake Havasu). Model output is used for annual and monthly decision support for mid-term operations (looking out 1 to 2 years).</lakeMeadStatic11>   <lakeMeadStatic12>The 24-Month Study utilizes forecasted Upper Basin inflow hydrology (provided by the &lt;a href="http://www.cbrfc.noaa.gov/" target="_blank"&gt;Colorado Basin River Forecast Center&lt;/a&gt;), projected reservoir operations, projected diversion and consumptive use schedules, and other factors, to generate a single scenario of potential reservoir conditions.</lakeMeadStatic12>   <lakeMeadStatic13>As Lake Mead's elevation declines, the Lower Basin comes closer to its first ever shortage condition. The annual operating conditions for Lake Mead and Lake Powell in the upcoming year are based on projected January 1 reservoir elevations from the August 24-Month Study consistent with the 2007 Record of Decision on Colorado River Interim Guidelines for Lower Basin Shortages and the Coordinated Operations for Lake Powell and Lake Mead (&lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/programs/strategies.html" target="_blank"&gt;2007 Interim Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;). The January 1 projections and resulting annual operation for Lake Mead and Lake Powell are reported in the Annual Operating Plan for Colorado River Reservoirs (AOP) for the upcoming year. The &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/AOP2016/AOP16_draft.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;draft 2016 AOP&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/aop/AOP15.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;2015 AOP&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/aop/index.html" target="_blank"&gt;previous years' AOPs&lt;/a&gt; can be found on Reclamation's website.</lakeMeadStatic13>   <lakeMeadStatic14>In addition to impacting water supply, impacts of changing reservoir levels also extend to the aquatic ecosystem. Water level changes and natural disturbances, such as storm events and resulting local runoff, can re-suspend sediments. Because some Lake Mead sediments contain contaminants, re-suspension of sediment may be of concern to ecological health (&lt;a href="http://pubs.usgs.gov/circ/1381/pdf/circ1381.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;U.S. Geological Survey, 2012&lt;/a&gt;).</lakeMeadStatic14>   <lakeMeadAnimated1>The Colorado River is one of the the principal sources of water for irrigation and domestic use in Arizona, southern California, southern Nevada, and portions of northwestern Mexico.</lakeMeadAnimated1>   <lakeMeadAnimated2>On behalf of the Secretary of the Interior, and pursuant to the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/pao/pdfiles/supctdec.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Consolidated Decree of the U.S. Supreme Court in Arizona v. California (547 U.S. 150 (2006))&lt;/a&gt;, Reclamation's Lower Colorado Region annually provides detailed and accurate records of diversions, return flows, and consumptive use of water delivered from the mainstream of the Colorado River below Lees Ferry to entitlement holders within the Lower Colorado River Basin.</lakeMeadAnimated2>   <lakeMeadAnimated3>The pictogram above depicts average consumptive use by select Lower Colorado River water entitlement holders for the 5-year period from 2010-2014. Each blue block represents a volume of 100,000 acre feet and partially shaded blue blocks represent volumes less than 100,000 acre-feet. Mouse over the bars to see the average consumptive use (2010-2014) by select Lower Colorado River entitlement holders (highlighted in yellow).</lakeMeadAnimated3>   <lakeMeadAnimated4>Click &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/wtracct.html" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about Lower Colorado River Water Accounting reports and click &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/contracts/entitlements.html" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about Lower Colorado River water entitlements and water delivery contracts.</lakeMeadAnimated4>   <lakeMeadAnimated5>The pictogram above depicts the elevation range (from approximately 1,200 to 1,229 feet) and annual water deliveries in the Lower Basin when Lake Mead is operating in a Flood Control Surplus Condition. Blue boxes represent delivery to states (not to specific locations within states). When in flood control, Lake Mead's operations are coordinated with the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, pursuant to the 1984 Field Working Agreement between Reclamation and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers.</lakeMeadAnimated5>   <lakeMeadAnimated6>The operating condition of Lake Mead for the upcoming year is determined by the projected January 1 elevation from Reclamation's August 24-Month Study, consistent with the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/programs/strategies.html" target="_blank"&gt;2007 Interim Guidelines&lt;/a&gt; and as reported in the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/aop/AOP15.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Annual Operating Plan for Colorado River Reservoirs (AOP)&lt;/a&gt;. The 2007 Interim Guidelines, adopted in December 2007 and in effect for an interim period through 2026, provide an objective methodology for determining the operating conditions and annual releases from Lake Powell and Lake Mead throughout the full range of reservoir operations, including low reservoir conditions. The 2007 Interim Guidelines also include criteria for implementing shortage and surplus conditions in the Lower Colorado River Basin.</lakeMeadAnimated6>   <lakeMeadAnimated7>In accordance with the &lt;a href="http://www.ibwc.state.gov/Files/1944Treaty.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;1944 U.S.-Mexico Water Treaty&lt;/a&gt;, when Lake Mead is operating in flood control, an additional 200,000 acre-feet of water will be delivered to Mexico for a total annual delivery of 1.7 maf.</lakeMeadAnimated7>   <lakeMeadAnimated8>A Quantified Surplus Condition or Domestic Surplus Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation for the upcoming year is projected to be between 1,145 feet and approximately 1,200 feet. In a surplus condition, entitlement holders in the Lower Basin may take delivery of additional water consistent with applicable surplus entitlements. Click &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/contracts/entitlements.html" target="_blank"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; to find out more about Lower Colorado River water entitlements, surplus entitlements, and water delivery contracts.</lakeMeadAnimated8>   <lakeMeadAnimated9>Consistent with Minute 319 to the 1944 U.S.-Mexico Water Treaty, Mexico may also take delivery of additional water within this elevation range.</lakeMeadAnimated9>   <lakeMeadAnimated10>Please visit the &lt;a href="http://www.ibwc.state.gov/home.html" target="_blank"&gt;International Boundary and Water Commission website&lt;/a&gt; to learn more about the 1944 U.S.-Mexico Water Treaty and &lt;a href="http://www.ibwc.gov/Files/Minutes/Minute_319.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Minute 319&lt;/a&gt; (in effect through 2017).</lakeMeadAnimated10>   <lakeMeadAnimated11>A Normal Condition or Intentionally Created Surplus (ICS) Surplus Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation for the upcoming year is projected to be between 1,075 and 1,145 feet. In a Normal/ICS Surplus Condition, water deliveries in the Lower Basin during the calendar year are limited to 7.5 maf, plus or minus any credits for ICS creation or delivery.</lakeMeadAnimated11>   <lakeMeadAnimated12>In accordance with the 1944 U.S.-Mexico Water Treaty, when Lake Mead is not in a Flood Control Condition, water deliveries to Mexico during the calendar year are limited to 1.5 maf, plus or minus any water deferred, Intentionally Created MexicPursuant to the 2007 Interim Guidelines, a Lower Basin Shortage Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation for the upcoming year is projected to be 1,075 feet or below. A Level 1 Shortage Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be between elevations 1,050 and 1,075 feet. Annual delivery reductions for Nevada and Arizona are 13,000 acre-feet and 320,000 acre-feet, respectively.an Allocation (ICMA) created, or additional water delivered pursuant to Sections III.1 and III.4 of Minute 319.</lakeMeadAnimated12>   <lakeMeadAnimated13>Pursuant to the 2007 Interim Guidelines, a Lower Basin Shortage Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation for the upcoming year is projected to be 1,075 feet or below. A Level 1 Shortage Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be between elevations 1,050 and 1,075 feet. Annual delivery reductions for Nevada and Arizona are 13,000 acre-feet and 320,000 acre-feet, respectively.</lakeMeadAnimated13>   <lakeMeadAnimated14>Pursuant to Minute 319, when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be between elevations 1,050 and 1,075 feet, Mexico's annual delivery may be reduced by 50,000 acre-feet. This delivery reduction may be offset by delivery of ICMA or water deferred under Section III.1 for a total annual delivery of 1.5 maf.</lakeMeadAnimated14>   <lakeMeadAnimated15>Pursuant to the 2007 Interim Guidelines, a Level 2 Shortage Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be between elevations 1,025 and 1,050 feet. Annual delivery reductions for Nevada and Arizona are 17,000 acre-feet and 400,000 acre-feet, respectively.</lakeMeadAnimated15>   <lakeMeadAnimated16>Pursuant to Minute 319, when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be between elevations 1,025 and 1,050 feet, Mexico's annual delivery may be reduced by 70,000 acre-feet. This delivery reduction may be offset by delivery of ICMA or water deferred under Section III.1 for a total annual delivery of 1.5 maf.</lakeMeadAnimated16>   <lakeMeadAnimated17>Pursuant to the 2007 Interim Guidelines, a Level 3 Shortage Condition exists when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be below elevation 1,025 feet. Annual delivery reductions for Nevada and Arizona are 20,000 acre-feet and 480,000 acre-feet, respectively. In addition, if Lake Mead is below elevation 1,025 feet, the Secretary of the Interior shall consult with the seven Colorado River Basin States to consider further measures consistent with applicable Federal law.</lakeMeadAnimated17>   <lakeMeadAnimated18>Pursuant to Minute 319, when Lake Mead's January 1 elevation is projected to be below elevation 1,025 feet, Mexico's annual delivery may be reduced by 125,000 acre-feet. This delivery reduction may be offset by delivery of ICMA or water deferred under Section III.1 for a total annual delivery of 1.5 maf.</lakeMeadAnimated18>   <lakeMeadAnimated19>To learn more about Lower Colorado River water entitlement holders and consumptive use data from the Bureau of Reclamation, click button below.</lakeMeadAnimated19>   <endEra>An era of hope - communication, cooperation, and collaboration.</endEra>   <credits1>In the Colorado River Basin, Reclamation is collaborating with its stakeholders on a number of projects, including developing creative strategies to reduce the impacts of drought and increase reservoir storage at Lake Powell and Lake Mead. Activities related to drought response include a system conservation program and drought contingency planning efforts in both basins. Additional ongoing activities are being conducted with stakeholders through the Basin Study Moving Forward process and with Native American Tribes through the Ten Tribes Partnership Tribal Water Study. Lastly, the implementation of Minute 319 and related binational discussions also underscore the importance of the partnership and continued collaboration between the United States and Mexico.</credits1>   <credits2>In 2014, an $11 million funding agreement for &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/newsroom/newsrelease/detail.cfm?RecordID=48006" target="_blank"&gt;Pilot System Conservation Program (PSCP)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was executed among Reclamation, Central Arizona Water Conservation District (CAWCD), the Metropolitan Water District of Southern California (MWD), Denver Water (DW), and the Southern Nevada Water Authority (SNWA) (the Funding Partners). The PSCP establishes a mechanism for funding the creation of Colorado River system water through voluntary water conservation actions and reductions in water use beginning in 2015 and continuing through at least 2016.  The purpose of the PSCP is to explore and learn about the effectiveness of voluntary measures that could be used, when needed, to help maintain water levels in Lake Powell and Lake Mead above critical levels.  All water conserved as a result of the pilot program would be considered Colorado River system water.  Proposals under the PSCP have been received from potential program participants in both the Upper and Lower Basins, where execution of implementation agreements began in 2015 and is ongoing.</credits2>   <credits3>In Lower Basin drought contingency planning, Reclamation is working with Arizona, California, and Nevada to identify proactive steps to lower the risk of reaching critical elevations at Lake Mead.  A step forward was a Memorandum of Understanding (MOU) for &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/g4000/LB_DroughtResponseMOU.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;Pilot Drought Response Actions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; signed by Reclamation and several water agencies in the Lower Basin States in December 2014. The MOU outlines a commitment by the parties to use best efforts to generate between 1.5 and 3.0 maf of additional water in Lake Mead through 2019.  Reclamation, MWD, SNWA, and CAWCD have agreed to take first steps to generate 0.740 maf of the additional water by the end of 2017. The MOU is an important step forward but a more comprehensive drought plan is currently being discussed with key water agencies in the Lower Basin.</credits3>   <credits4>In Upper Basin drought contingency planning, Colorado, New Mexico, Utah, and Wyoming are pursuing a plan with three major components: 1) extended operations of the Colorado River Storage Project (CRSP) reservoirs, 2) voluntary demand management (e.g., fallowing or deficit irrigation), and 3) augmentation (primarily weather modification, such as cloud seeding).  Reclamation, in collaboration with the Upper Basin States, has conducted modeling that indicates extended operations of the upper CRSP reservoirs to move water to Lake Powell can significantly reduce the probability of Lake Powell falling below critical elevations.  Reclamation, in consultation with the Upper Basin States, is developing an extended operations plan and implementation agreement.  It is anticipated that these will be completed by the end of 2015.</credits4>   <credits5>In addition to the previously mentioned activities, Congress has provided authorization for additional funding through Reclamation for drought-related activities to increase Colorado River system water in Lake Mead, Lake Powell, and other Colorado River system reservoirs for the benefit of the system.  This authorization requires that a report evaluating the effectiveness of the water conservation pilot projects be submitted to Congress in 2018, including a recommendation on whether the activities undertaken by the pilot projects should be continued. (Per the Consolidated and Further Continuing Appropriations Act, 2015 (Public Law 113-235, Div. D., Secs. 204-206), executed on December 16, 2014.)</credits5>   <credits6>In May 2013, Reclamation and Basin stakeholders initiated the Moving Forward effort to build on future considerations and next steps identified in the Colorado River Basin Study. The Moving Forward effort enhances the broad, inclusive stakeholder process demonstrated in the Basin Study with an ultimate goal of identifying actionable steps to address projected water supply and demand imbalances that have broad-based support and provide a wide range of benefits. The Moving Forward effort is being conducted in a phased approach. Phase 1 began with the formation of a Coordination Team and three multi-stakeholder workgroups that focus on water conservation, reuse and environmental and recreational flows. In May, 2015 the &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/programs/crbstudy/MovingForward/Phase1Report.html" target="_blank"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phase 1 Report&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; was published, which documents the activities and outcomes of the workgroups during this phase and includes opportunities for potential future action.</credits6>   <credits7>Begun in late 2013, the Colorado River Basin Ten Tribes Partnership Tribal Water Study is a cooperative effort with the Ten Tribes Partnership, whose members hold a significant amount of quantified and unquantified federal reserved water rights to the Colorado River and its tributaries. The study builds on the technical foundation of the Colorado River Basin Study by further assessing water supplies and demands for these tribes and identifies tribal opportunities and challenges associated with the development of tribal water. This study is anticipated to be completed in 2016.</credits7>   <credits8>In November 2012, the United States and Mexico reached agreement on &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/feature/minute319.html" target="_blank"&gt;Minute 319&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; to the 1944 U.S.-Mexico Water Treaty. Minute 319 is a five-year agreement (2013-2017) which provides for a series of joint cooperative actions between the United States and Mexico, including surplus sharing during higher Lake Mead conditions, reduced water deliveries during lower Lake Mead conditions, flexibility with the Intentionally Created Mexican Apportionment mechanism, opportunities for improved and more efficient infrastructure, and water for the environment. In 2014, pursuant to Section III.6.e.i of IBWC Minute No. 319, a &lt;a href="http://www.ibwc.state.gov/Files/Minutes/Min319_Fact_Sheet.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;pulse flow&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; of approximately 105,000 acre-feet was delivered to Mexico from March 23 through May 18 to benefit the riparian ecosystem in the Colorado River Delta. Implementation of the pulse flow also involved a &lt;a href="http://www.ibwc.gov/EMD/Min319Monitoring.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; component conducted by scientists and experts from the United States and Mexico to determine the environmental benefits of the pulse flow and the overall performance of the pilot project. With the success of the binational implementation of this project, the United States and Mexico hope to develop a new binational agreement in the spirit of continued collaboration to meet future challenges ahead.</credits8>   <credits9>Bureau of Reclamation System Conservation Pilot Program. &lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/newsroom/newsrelease/detail.cfm?RecordID=48006" target="_blank"&gt;October, 8, 2014 press release&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</credits9>   <credits10>2014 Pilot System Conservation Program Agreement</credits10>   <credits11>2014 Memorandum of Understanding for Lower Basin Pilot Drought Response Actions</credits11>   <credits12>Colorado River Basin Moving Forward Activities</credits12>   <credits13>Minute 319: Interior Secretary Salazar and Reclamation Commissioner Connor Join U.S. and Mexico Delegations for Historic Colorado River Water Agreement Ceremony.&lt;a href="http://www.usbr.gov/lc/region/feature/minute319.html" target="_blank"&gt;November 20, 2012 press release&lt;/a&gt;.</credits13>   <stickyNav1>Introduction</stickyNav1>   <stickyNav2>Lifeline</stickyNav2>   <stickyNav3>One river</stickyNav3>   <stickyNav4>Control structures</stickyNav4>   <stickyNav5>Extended drought</stickyNav5>   <stickyNav6>Water supply</stickyNav6>   <stickyNav7>Storage capacity</stickyNav7>   <stickyNav8>Supply &amp; demand</stickyNav8>   <stickyNav9>Declining storage</stickyNav9>   <stickyNav10>Shortage</stickyNav10>   <stickyNav11>Era of hope</stickyNav11> </fullText>