<?xml version="1.0"?>
 <fullText>   <siteTitle>OWDI Drought</siteTitle>   <readMore>Read More &gt;&gt;</readMore>   <hideText>Hide Text</hideText>   <welcomeText>Welcome to Colorado River Basin Drought</welcomeText>   <coDroughtHeader>Colorado River Basin Drought</coDroughtHeader>   <welcomeTitle>Drought in the Colorado River Basin</welcomeTitle>   <welcomeSub>Insights using open data</welcomeSub>   <scroll>Scroll down to view this application.</scroll>   <appExplanation1>Since 2000, the Colorado River Basin (Basin) has been experiencing an historic, extended drought that has impacted regional water supply and other resources, such as hydropower, recreation, and ecologic services. During this time, the Basin has experienced its lowest 16-year period of inflow in over 100 years of record keeping and reservoir storage in the Colorado River system has declined from nearly full to about half of capacity. Since 2000, the Colorado River Basin (Basin) has been experiencing an historic, extended drought that has impacted regional water supply and other resources, such as hydropower, recreation, and ecologic services. During this time, the Basin has experienced its lowest 16-year period of inflow in over 100 years of record keeping and reservoir storage in the Colorado River system has declined from nearly full to about half of capacity.</appExplanation1>   <appExplanation2>Entities that rely on Colorado River water are concerned with the impacts of the ongoing drought and declining reservoir levels, such as decreasing water supply and the possibility of a first ever shortage condition in the Lower Basin, decreasing hydropower capacities at Lake Powell and Lake Mead, the potential for loss of hydroelectric generation at Lake Powell, reduced recreational opportunities, and changes to in-stream flows that support ecologic services.</appExplanation2>   <appExplanation3>In response to drought conditions, Federal agencies and stakeholders throughout the Basin have been working together to find creative ways to reduce the impacts of the drought for the people and resources that rely on water from the Colorado River.</appExplanation3>   <appExplanation4>This Colorado River Basin Drought Visualization, developed by the Department of the Interior (Department), the U.S. Geological Survey (USGS), and the Bureau of Reclamation (Reclamation), is a Pilot Project to support the Department&#x2019;s Open Water Data Initiative (OWDI). The Pilot Project is part of a multi-agency effort to showcase the usefulness of open data (i.e., data provided in a discoverable, sharable, and machine-readable format) by exploring the current 16-year drought and its impacts in the Colorado River Basin.</appExplanation4>   <appExplanation5>Scroll down to learn more about the importance of the Colorado River, the impacts of the current drought, and the ways in which the drought is being managed in the Basin.</appExplanation5>   <appExplanation6>For more information about the OWDI, please visit the Advisory Committee on Water Information &lt;a href="http://acwi.gov/spatial/owdi/" target="_blank"&gt;OWDI website&lt;/a&gt;.</appExplanation6> </fullText>